For a long time, one of the comforting
things about brain organoids is that
their brain waves really aren't very
complicated. In fact, they look very
much like that of somebody in a coma and
have also been compared to a pre-term
baby. But since then, we have discovered
that the more complex they get or if
they're interacted with or if they're
just put in a body, they do become more
complex.
Their brain waves actually do look very
much like that of a pre-term baby and we
only know that because when a baby is
born pre-term, you can do an EEG. Prior
to that, it's a little difficult cuz you
know, they're kind of inside somewhere.
Now, John Hopkins did claim last year
that they created a brain organoid that
was comparable to that of a 40-day old
fetus.
Yes, it had multiple brain regions and
you can kind of lob different kinds of
brain organoids together to create one
brain. It's a little difficult to grow
everything properly all together. Yes,
it had all the brain regions you might
expect as well as 80% of the total cells
that they wanted to do to accomplish to
get to that mark of a 40-day old fetus.
The next goal is to create one that is 1
cm across and that is a mouse brain
size. Now, that should be concerning
because mice are capable of quite a bit
of consciousness, but it's also not
going to be interacted with. So,
essentially, it's just sitting in a
void. If it were capable of some amount
of consciousness, it's not being given
enough stimulus to be able to experience
it.
And a lot of people ask, are those eyes?
Yes, they are eyes. Your eyes are kind
of part of your nervous system and they
are a nervous system organoid.
This is essentially growing a brain
without the typical body around it and
you might be concerned about the ethics
and yes, lots of people are concerned
about the ethics of creating them. But
the answer is that we're not there yet.
When we go too far, I'm sure we'll know
it. One of the really interesting things
to me about these is that they don't
really care what they're interfacing
with. And yes, there's multiple ways to
put them together. You can connect them
by axons, so little connections between
the brain organoids.
Those ones will develop more complex
signaling and they'll all behave as one
when they're connected. This also
provides the additional benefit that if
one of them, you know, expire, you can
put in another one and the old ones can
train the new ones.
An AI can also train them or an AI can
direct them or they can direct an AI.
I've talked about this stuff. However,
once they get large enough, the inner
core begins to die off. They suffer from
hypoxia. Without a vascular system, they
cannot survive. And that has been
largely helped by recent research
combining them with vascular organoids.
And you know, the tech industry has
decided to fix this problem by making
them two-dimensional. And that does seem
to work. And I wonder if there's going
to be a unique form of cognition that
comes out of two-dimensional organoids
versus three-dimensional. I do not know,
but there are many questions to be
asked. One other solution is just to put
them in a mouse.
I mean, they can be put in monkeys and
that research has been done, too. And
one day, they will be a treatment for
strokes because they seem to be very
effective at treating strokes in animal
models. Stem cell trials have been going
on for at least a decade where they try
to fix stem cells in the brain and they
don't usually survive. It seems they do
better if they have a little chance to
become something. If they start out as a
fetal organoid of something that looks
very much like a fetus, they end up
being kind of invasive to the brain.
Not in a bad way. I mean, they did make
projections all over the place. It seems
that the fetal cells are a little more
aggressive than the adult cells and that
is concerning too because that could end
up being tumor territory, which is why
it's good not to just immediately jump
to human trials. If placed in a mouse,
though, yeah, they will integrate with
the rest of the mouse's brain and the
brain waves in that organoid will become
as complex as the rest of the mouse's
brain. Without interaction, without
something to do, our brains atrophy and
we see that. We see that every day. If
you don't do math, you forget how to do
math. And people who are born in
profoundly isolated environments do not
develop normally.
So, you could imagine even And a brain
organoid were capable of ultimate
consciousness, whatever consciousness
is, I mean, we don't really have a great
definition for it, not having any
interaction would probably prevent that.
That part actually bumps me out because
brain organoids have been put in all
sorts of things, spider robots and pong,
other video games were similar to
Pac-Man and Doom. But the most complex
brain organoids, the largest ones,
they're not doing anything. They're just
sitting in nothingness and that gives me
more anxiety than I'd like to admit.
Now researchers did realize early on in
brain organoids that if you engage with
them, they become more complex and that
part made sense.
More recently, it's been discovered that
if you give them more of a body, they
become more complex. Some researchers
gave them a nervous system of sorts, a
spinal cord organoid and I don't love
this research because they were testing
pain on it. And that is just because
this could be a potential model to
figure out what helps pain. They're not
treating it as a conscious or sentient
organism or a lab animal. So, it's not
unethical in that regard.
Does it make me profoundly uncomfortable
and do I think this kind of research
should be carried out? I can see the
positive outcomes to it, but if there is
some kind of sentience that we are not
acknowledging, then maybe it's not
ethical. And of course, some researchers
have claimed sentience.
So, yes, they will happily integrate,
which is a really positive sign. It also
gives us a way to study organoids in a
long-term survival situation where we
don't really have to worry about keeping
it alive.
Also, the little helmet that the mouse
wore is kind of adorable. I'm not going
to lie there.
It's only weirder when you think about
all the implications, but just it's
cute. A big question people ask is
whether or not the brain organoid could
act as a parasite, and no, probably not.
If you take a mouse that has Parkinson's
and you give it a functional brain
organoid, even if it comes from a human,
then yes, it can alleviate the
Parkinson's symptoms.
So, it seems it is working with the
mouse rather than just taking over, but
it can influence behavior. When it comes
to a more complete human brain inside of
a mouse, if you want to know what the
outcome of that is, then yes, we have
humanized mice by giving them human
neurons during development, and they do
end up smarter.
That research is usually limited because
you have to have a great justification
for it, and creating humanized animals
has a great possibility for harm.
So, not often done, but I do think about
it a lot. My question is if we took the
two genes that are necessary for human
speech, you know, the ones that give
mice more complex vocalizations and gave
them human neurons, what would happen?
And what if we did that to other
animals? And when I think about it, I
realize it's probably good that this has
not happened, but I still wonder about
it. I cannot tell you how to feel about
this topic, and on the one hand, I can
see the enormous potential for harm that
could be done as well as the benefit
from medical research. I think in the
next few years, we're really going to
figure out whether or not this was a
good idea or not, and it is rapidly
progressing, and that that part worries
me. I find all of this both fascinating
and existentially deranged. I will also
direct you to the description because I
provide citations for everything I talk
about every time.
The last video had 17, so if you're
interested in reading about this stuff,
just pop over there, and the citations
within the citations can take you to
other really cool papers.
Google is just not going to get you
exactly what you want. Either way, I
hope you've enjoyed this. I will keep
you up to date. You have no choice.
Hello from Earth.
>> Are you calling audio
because of the tiny prokaryotes swarming
in the culture?